<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Liu Lab</title>
    <link>/</link>
      <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Liu Lab</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hua2ec155b4296a9c9791d015323e16eb5_11927_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Liu Lab</title>
      <link>/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Wheat Projects</title>
      <link>/project/wheat-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/wheat-project/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;wheat-leaf-rust-and-yellow-rust&#34;&gt;Wheat Leaf Rust and Yellow Rust&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gene mapping is a process to find trait-associated genetic markers. The gene
mapping process is an important step towards identifying genes responsible for
phenotypic traits. In wheat, identification of effective (or polymorphic)
genetic markers and gene mapping are tedious. The BSR-Seq analysis, combining
RNA-Seq and bulked segregant analysis, was developed and has been successfully
used to facilitate mapping and cloning many genes in species other than wheat.
This project is to adapt this method to the wheat system. Currently, we are
applying BSR-Seq to map several genes in wheat, including leaf rust gene Lr42
and several unknown yellow rust genes in a diploid wild relative of wheat.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Maize Projects</title>
      <link>/project/maize-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/maize-project/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;maize-embryogenesis-and-regeneration&#34;&gt;Maize Embryogenesis and Regeneration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CRISPRs provide great potential for the elucidation of maize gene functions and
trait improvements. However, current genetic and genomic resources as well as
transformation capacity in maize are insufficient for the full utilization of
genome engineering tools. We are generating public resources that include a
high-quality genome assembly of a highly transformation amenable maize inbred
line A188 and double haploid (DH) lines from a cross of A188 with B73, a
transformation recalcitrant inbred variety and the maize reference genome. We
are genetically mapping the genetic elements controlling embryogenesis and
regeneration. Our goal is to identify genes through map-based cloning with the
assistance from multilayered gene regulatory networks, and apply the genes to
enhance maize transformation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;maize-diseases---gosss-wilts&#34;&gt;Maize Diseases - Goss&amp;rsquo;s Wilts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Goss’s wilt is a maize disease, caused by Clavibacter michiganensis subsp.
nebraskensis (CMN) that was first identified in 1969. The disease has not been a
serious problem until recent re-emergence in the Great Plains region. While a
number of Clavibacter-related diseases have been characterized, few genetic
resources have been identified specifically for Goss’s wilt. We performed
traditional GWAS, traditional QTL, XP-GWAS, XP-CNV to dissect disease
resistance. Meanwhile, we performed genome sequencing for multiple Cmn strains.
Our project goal is to provide extensive genetic information into plant
resistance and bacterial virulence with regard to the re-emergence of Goss&amp;rsquo;s
Wilt disease of maize. Our ultimate goal is to identify resistance genes in
plant host and virulence elements in bacteria.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;genomic-structural-variation&#34;&gt;Genomic Structural Variation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Genomes contain structural variations (SV) that are comprised of unbalanced
forms (copy number variation) and balanced forms (sequences in same copy number
but at different genomic locations), and SV has been implicated in phenotype
variation. However, SV often occurs on a scale that is difficult to be
characterized with a single approach. We are attempting to combine multiple
approaches, next-generation sequencing, genetic approach, and BioNano genome
mapping technology to characterize SV.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;change-in-gene-expression-in-maize-under-abiotic-conditions&#34;&gt;Change in Gene Expression in Maize Under Abiotic Conditions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The genome-wide messenger RNA expression (mRNA), including splicing events, and
small RNA (sRNA) expression are tractable at the unprecedented level with the
utility of the next-generation sequencing technology. This project is designed
to measure mRNA and sRNA from plant individuals under different controlled
abiotic stresses. Through quantifying the change in the expression of genes,
splicing sites, and sRNAs in response to abiotic conditions, we hope to find
some candidates as the targets that can be used to enhance plant tolerance to
extremely environmental conditions. sRNA and mRNA co-expression networks were
also constructed to understand the change in expression correlation under
drought condition.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pathogen Projects</title>
      <link>/project/pathogen-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/pathogen-project/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;biology-of-mini-chromosomes-in-the-fungus-causing-blast-diseases&#34;&gt;Biology of mini-chromosomes in the fungus causing blast diseases&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We recently reported a high-quality genome assembly of an aggressive, recently-isolated wheat blast strain plus the first assembled mini-chromosome sequence for the blast pathogen. We hypothesize the crosstalk between mini-chromosomes and core-chromosomes resulting in effector gene sequence variability and reshuffling with impacts on pathogen aggressiveness and host selectivity. The hypothesis will be tested through genetic, genomic, and cytological approaches.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
